Well
yeah because July 1st 1867 was when Canada was created.
I thought it was in Boston.
I was
in
France on Bastille Day a few years ago.
That was very impressive. Okay I think we're
working. If not, what can I do?
Okay today where are we up to?
Good morning everybody.
Today's דף Daf is יג, Yud Gimmel, thirteen.
I think you're correct.
We were right at the bottom of the page,
the end of the line. אמר רב אשי. Amar Rav Ashi.
Yes, אמר רב אשי. Amar Rav Ashi. Where in the סוגיא Sugya
is that? I have this.
Near the
bottom of twelve B, יב עמוד ב. Yud Beis Amud Beis. It
is one,
two,
three, four, six lines from the bottom, three words in.
אמר רב
אשי.
Amar Rav
Ashi. So we've been discussing how
much
witnesses are allowed to be off in their determination of the time
and we had different opinions whether several hours
and depending on whether it's the same time of day, in other
words day as opposed to night, would definitely be a contradiction between
two witnesses. And the context of all this of course is determining
the rule about חמץ. Chametz. When do you have to stop eating
חמץ Chametz and is it relevant that people would make a mistake?
If they think it's if you're supposed to stop at the fifth
hour or at the sixth hour then how exact are people's timekeeping
abilities? So רב אשי Rav Ashi says כמחלוקת בעדות כך מחלוקת בחמץ.
Kamachloket B'Edus Kach Machloket B'Chametz. Whatever the rule is, whatever the argument
is about עדות Edus and the contradicting or how far off we
can allow witnesses to be, same thing with חמץ. Chametz. In other
words if you hold that you're allowed to be an hour off,
then you would say that you have to stop eating an hour
before the time.
פשיטא Peshita says the גמרא. Gemara. Well of course that's the whole
reason we've been discussing this whole issue because we want to apply
to חמץ. Chametz. היינו דקאמרינן, Hainu Dach Amrinan, that's what we've been
saying all along. So גמרא Gemara says הא קמשמע לן Ha Kamashmalan
what is it telling us? שינויי דשנינן שינוייא הוא ולא תימא תנאי
היא.
Shinui Deshaninan Shinuya Hu V'lo Teima Tanai
Hi. You might have thought that maybe there's a מחלוקת תנאים Machlokas
Tannaim whether you can apply that same, the same rules about עדות
Edus to חמץ Chametz and perhaps that's the מחלוקת. Machlokas. In other
words, can you apply that or not? So what the גמרא Gemara
is just letting you know at the end is no it's not
a מחלוקת תנאים Machlokas Tannaim about whether to apply this. You apply
it. The מחלוקת Machlokas is about when do we consider עדות Edus
contradictory, how far off do we allow them to be in their
testimony and that same rule applies to חמץ. Chametz. אמר רב שימי
בר אשי Amar Rav Shimi Bar Ashi לא שנו אלא בשעות. Lo
Shanu Ela B'Shaos.
So we were talking about how many hours you can allow them
to be off without damaging their credibility. אבל אחד אומר קודם הנץ
החמה ואחד אומר אחר הנץ החמה, Aval Echad Omer Kodem HaNetz HaChama
V'Echad Omer Achar HaNetz HaChama, if one says it was before sunrise
and the other says after sunrise, עדותם בטילה. Edusam Beteila. Then that's
a contradiction and those two עדים Eidim are not compatible. You cannot
accept their testimony. פשיטא, Peshita, this is obvious right? I mean what
could be more obvious? One says it's day, one says it's night.
אלא אחד אומר קודם הנץ החמה ואחד אומר בתוך הנץ החמה, Ela
Echad Omer Kodem HaNetz HaChama V'Echad Omer B'Toch HaNetz HaChama, עדותם בטילה.
Edusam Beteila. What do we mean to say? If one says it
was before sunrise and the other one says during sunrise, so is
that contradictory? So yes that is contradictory, עדותם בטילה. Edusam Beteila. הא
נמי פשיטא, Hannami Peshita, גמרא Gemara says so what, so that's also
obvious. One says it was nighttime and the other says it was
daybreak. That seems to be self-evident that it's contradictory. גמרא Gemara answers
מהו דתימא תרווייהו חדא מילתא קאמרי. Ma DeTeima Tarvaihu Chada Milsa Kamri.
Maybe I would have thought that they're both really saying the same
thing when one says it was before sunrise and the other says
during sunrise, maybe they mean the same thing. והאי דקאמר בתוך הנץ
החמה, VeHai Dekamar B'Toch HaNetz HaChama, the one who said it was
during sunrise, בגילוייא הוה קאמר. Bigiluya Hava Ka Amar. He was talking
about the glow, is the way Artscroll translates this word גילויא. Giluya.
וזהרורי בעלמא הוא דחזא. VeZahrurei BeAlma Hu DeChaza.
He did not see the sun rise. He saw, it's like the
dawn, the light of the dawn. He saw the rays of the
sun but the sun was still below the horizon. So if one
says בתוך הנץ החמה, B'Toch HaNetz HaChama, it was during the sunrise,
then he, you may have
thought... so this comes to tell you that עדות שבטלה, Edut shebtela,
that if he expresses himself that way,
that it was during the sunrise, we interpret that to mean the
sun had actually begun to rise, and that would contradict the other
witness who said before the sun rise. So the same difficulty we
raised yesterday, like just ask him, you know, what did you mean?
Or maybe if it was a farmer or someone who's a shepherd
person, they'd be more attuned to this by eye than a groundling
or a city dweller.
So again, that's another factor, you know, should we shouldn't we consider
all those factors? Why are we trying to establish a blanket rule
about theoretical testimony?
Same issue we raised yesterday which we didn't really have a resolution
to.
Theoretical testimony. Theoretical testimony.
Yeah, we're talking about a theoretical case, so you can't inquire further
about a theoretical case.
Yeah, yeah, I understand, but why are you trying to establish an
abstract rule about
testimony that may or may not occur
if presumably you'd be able to verify the details. It's fine to
establish abstract rules to determine what's the, you know, what are the
rules, what's the הלכה halakha or whatever, but I don't really understand
how this applies to the way witnesses express themselves in the abstract.
Maybe it's not abstract. Maybe this is a segment of a concrete
series
of questions, like what time was it? And what do you mean
sunrise? Like what did the world look like? And if in the
end he says בתוך הנץ החמה, betoch hanetz hachama, that's a definite
meaning. Two witnesses saying the same thing gives you accuracy. In other
words,
maybe what we're getting is... oh, so you're saying...
so it's like if I were to say it's half past ten,
you'd know that meant 10:30,
it can't mean something else. And besides, you don't want to lead
the witness, so to speak, I don't mean that phrase like literally
because it's not
in court, but like
you don't want...
you have to objectify somehow what he's saying. Because otherwise you'll put
words in his mouth and then you'll have ספק safek the other
direction. So maybe it's the opposite, it's not the abstract formulation, but
it's at a certain point in the context of all those חקירות
hakirot or דרישות. drishot. If he says it that way, that's it.
Okay. אמר
רב נחמן אמר רב,
Amar Rav Nachman amar
Rav, הלכה כרבי
יהודה.
Halacha k'Rabbi
Yehuda.
Rav Nachman says the הלכה Halacha is like Rabbi Yehuda, that you
wait... you can eat them until the beginning of the fifth hour
and you have an hour to
hang
around and then you burn it at the end of the fifth
hour. אמר ליה רבא לרב נחמן, Amar lei Rava le-Rav Nachman, ונימא
אמר הלכה כרבי מאיר, ve-neima amar Halacha k'Rabbi Meir, דסתם לן תנא
כוותיה? desastam la Tanna k'vateih? Why are you פסקנינג paskening like Rabbi
Yehuda? Say that the הלכה Halacha is like Rabbi Meir because there
is a סתם משנה Stam Mishna that goes according to the view
of Rabbi Meir. What is that משנה? Mishna? דתנן, Detnan, כל שעה
שמותר לאכול
מאכיל.
kol sha'ah she-mutar
le-ekhol ma'akhil. The משנה Mishna says as long as you are permitted
to eat, you can feed the... you can feed your חמץ chametz
to your animals or you can have הנאה hana'ah from it.
Don't they say usually the סתם משנה Stam Mishna is Rabbi Meir?
Yeah, I know, it's a little weird, right?
But... Meir says this himself?
No, that's true, but if you have something quoted in the name
of Rabbi Meir, then that doesn't have the rule applied to it.
So, yes, so we have a סתם משנה Stam Mishna and we
usually say הלכה כסתם משנה, Halacha k'Stam Mishna, and the סתם משנה
Stam Mishna implies that as long as you can eat, you can
use it, so that would imply that there is no... none of
this תולין כל חמש, tolin kol chamesh, that you don't have the
fifth hour of limbo.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, ההיא לאו סתמא היא, ha'hi lav
stama hi, that is not considered a סתם משנה, Stam Mishna, משום
דקשיא מותר, mishum de-kashi mutar,
because of the phrasing it says מותר לאכול. mutar le-ekhol.
Look at רש"י, Rashi, משום דקשיא מותר mishum de-kashi mutar בפרק כל
שעה מקשינן, be-Perek Kol Sha'ah makshinan, כל שעה שאוכל מאכיל מיבעי ליה.
kol sha'ah she-okhel ma'akhil mibayei lei. The גמרא Gemara
in the other פרק perek
makes this more explicit, it should have said as long as you
eat, כל שעה שאוכל. kol sha'ah she-okhel. Why does it say כל
שעה שמותר לאכול? kol sha'ah she-mutar le-ekhol? ומותר משמע, U-mutar mashma, כל
שעה שמותר אדם אחר לאכול, kol sha'ah she-mutar adam acher le-ekhol,
as long as there is someone who is allowed to eat,
מאכיל זה האסור. ma'akhil zeh ha-asur. No
you
can't, so that's not like the רבי. Rebbi. Right. And so it's
and
so it's talking about a כהן, kohen, right? A כהן kohen can
eat,
which is the third opinion in our משנה, mishnah, so it's not
like...
Right. Right. So the... exactly.
So then ונימא מר הלכה כרבן גמליאל דהוה ליה מכריע. veneima mar
halachah keRabban Gamliel dehavei lei machria. So alright, so we have two
competing opinions, we should say the הלכה halachah is like רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel who decides like one of the opinions.
אמר ליה רבן גמליאל לאו מכריע הוא טעמא דנפשיה קאמר. amar lei
Rabban Gamliel lav machria hu tama denafshei ka'amar. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
is not a מכריע. machria. He's not tipping the balance between one
or the other. He's the third opinion. The third opinion is not
a מכריע. machria.
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel was תולה חולין כל ארבע תרומה כל חמש.
toleh chullin kol arba terumah kol chamesh.
Is he not talking about חמץ chametz there? רבן גמליאל? Rabban Gamliel?
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, he's talking about חמץ.
chametz. Oh,
okay. Yeah. But since he's...
no, since he's... since he doesn't mention anything about תרומה, terumah,
then he's talking about his own opinion. אי בעית אימא, i ba'it
eima, or you could say רב דאמר כי האי תנא. Rav de'amar
ki hai tanna. רב, Rav, who is establishing the הלכה halachah like
רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, has a different opinion
about... or is following a different תנא tanna in order to decide
the הלכה. halachah. דתניא, detanya, what's the ברייתא? braisa? ארבעה עשר שחל
להיות בשבת מבערים את הכל מלפני שבת. arba'ah asar shechal lihyot beShabbos
meva'arim es hakol milifnei Shabbos. Fourteenth ערב פסח Erev Pesach is on
שבת, Shabbos, you destroy the חמץ chametz before שבת, Shabbos, you have
to do it before שבת Shabbos because you can't burn it on
שבת. Shabbos. ושרפים תרומות טמאות תלויות וטהורות. vesorfim terumos teme'os teluyos utehoros.
And on the thirteenth, on ערב שבת, Erev Shabbos, you burn תרומה
terumah which is טמא, tamei,
and תרומה terumah which is טהור, tahor, and תרומה terumah which is
תלוי, taluy, which is like it's unclear. You have a doubt whether
it's טמא tamei or טהור. tahor.
ומשיירין מן הטהורות מזון שתי סעודות. umeshayrin min hatehoros mazon shtei se'udos.
What you do is you leave over, presuming you have a כהן
kohen or you are a כהן, kohen, then you leave over from
the תרומה טהורה terumah tehorah
enough for two meals, for Friday night and for שבת Shabbos morning.
כדי לאכול עד ארבע שעות kedei le'echol ad arba sha'os so that
you can eat until the fourth hour on שבת Shabbos ערב פסח.
Erev Pesach. דברי רבי אלעזר בן יהודה איש ברתותא
שאמר משום רבי יהושע.
divrei Rebbi Elazar ben Yehuda ish
Bartosa she'amar mishum Rebbi Yehoshua.
This is the opinion of רבי אלעזר. Rebbi Elazar. אמרו לו טהורות
לא ישרפו שמא ימצאו להן אוכלים. amru lo tehoros lo yisarefu shema
yimtzu lahen ochlim.
So they objected and said to him, well why are you burning...
you're not supposed to burn תרומה, terumah, you're not supposed to destroy
תרומה terumah
absent the circumstances of the איסור חמץ, issur chametz, so leave all
the תרומה terumah which is still edible until the morning,
because maybe maybe some כהנים kohanim will come by for breakfast and
you'll be able to feed it to them, and so you're burning
it too early, you're burning it before the deadline. Yeah?
Yeah, but we don't do that if we have...
but we don't have the issue of תרומה. terumah.
But we put aside חלה challah to eat on שבת. Shabbos.
We don't
do ביעור חמץ bi'ur chametz of everything.
Well we do בדיקת
חמץ bedikat chametz but we still save חלה, challah, which is not
תרומה. terumah.
Right, right, but this is applying
to... I think what it means is you burn everything, I mean,
תרומה terumah is a special circumstance.
No, no, no, I think what they're dealing with תרומה terumah because
there is a prohibition against destroying the תרומה. terumah. Yeah, but I
think the assumption is...
what about when we have this that situation,
which we have every few years, where we put aside חלה challah
rolls? Yes. And so we don't destroy them before שבת. Shabbos.
No, but it's saying even the basic opinion here, the first opinion
is that you do leave over enough for dinner and breakfast of
תרומה.
terumah. Yeah, but isn't he saying ארבעה עשר שחל להיות בשבת מבערים
את הכל? arba'ah asar shechal lihyot beShabbos meva'arim es hakol?
Yeah, yeah,
but continue, ושרפים תרומה ומשיירין מן הטהורות מזון שתי סעודות. vesorfim terumah
umeshayrin min hatehoros mazon shtei se'udos. You have to read the whole
sentence.
But she's saying ומן הטהורות. umin hatehoros. Yes.
What she's saying is, imagine for once the כהן kohen has תרומה
terumah and חולין, chullin, get rid of all the חולין chullin but
not all the תרומה. terumah.
But we don't get rid of all our חמץ chametz in that
case, we set aside חלה. challah.
I don't understand your objection because that's what this ברייתא braisa is
saying.
No, but she's saying it applies only to the תרומות טהורות. terumos
tehoros. Yes.
So what she's saying is... alright, so let's say, alright, so let's
say, let's say you're a
כהן, kohen, yes, as opposed to me, who will never have תרומה,
terumah, so in that kind of case...
then you're saying you don't have to be שורף soref them.
Right, meaning it may be a כהן kohen who has both, that's
what he's talking about. If you're a כהן kohen and you have
both,
what should you leave over? Obviously you should leave over
the
תרומה terumah because... Right,
so I think Michael's correct. I think Michael's correct. If you have,
if you have חולין Chullin and תרומה Terumah and you need to
leave over some for the morning, what are you going to leave
over?
If you're a כהן, Kohen, you leave over תרומה.
Terumah. You leave over תרומה, Terumah, but but if you're
a non-כהן, Kohen, unless you assume this is this ברייתא Baraita or
whatever it is, משנה Mishnah is limited to כהנים. Kohanim.
Exactly, that's my point. Otherwise, a regular person, a non-כהן, Kohen, what
would be the point of leaving over תרומה? Terumah? You can't eat
it anyway.
But but in general, it's saying of course only the תרומה Terumah
would only apply to כהנים, Kohanim, but the חמץ Chametz ביעור Biur
at the point of it before שבת Shabbat doesn't that apply to
everyone?
I think you're reading it in isolation and not in context of
the whole of the whole ברייתא. Baraita. That's my understanding of it.
I think you have to read this ברייתא Baraita as applying only
to כהנים Kohanim who have תרומה. Terumah.
Why do the כהנים Kohanim have to get rid of all their
חמץ Chametz before שבת Shabbat and the non-כהנים Kohanim can keep their
חמץ? Chametz?
No, no, that's not what it says. This this ברייתא Baraita is
not dealing with other cases. I think the implication or the assumption
is that if you're not dealing with תרומה, Terumah, you're a regular,
you're a non-כהן, Kohen,
then you leave over whichever part you want. Now you do have
to, you do leave over food, you do.
But the משנה Mishnah says, it says, but I don't think it's
talking about non-כהנים Kohanim is what I'm saying. I think, I think
to me it's, it seems straightforward that we're this ברייתא's Baraita only
dealing with כהנים Kohanim who have תרומה. Terumah. And
it's not relevant. I don't, I don't agree with your deduction, but
you know that's.
But the ברייתא Baraita doesn't, doesn't sound like it's only speaking to
כהנים. Kohanim.
We'll see. I guess we'll see.
Well, maybe we'll פסקן pasken differently today.
Okay, so Rivka and I have a disagreement. We'll put it on
the side.
I don't know where this comes from.
Yeah, okay. We do a lot of things that are not in
the גמרא.
Gemara. Really?
Yeah, that's true. אמרו לו, Amru Lo, so they objected to רבי
אלעזר: Rabbi Elazar: טהורות לא ישרפו שמא ימצא להם אוכלים. Tehorot Lo
Yisrafu Shema Yimatzei Lahem Ochlim. Why are you burning the extra טהור
tahor תרומה Terumah before ערב פסח? Erev Pesach? Maybe somebody will come
over, a כהן Kohen will come over for breakfast and you'll be
able to feed him, so you're burning it too soon. אמר להן,
Amar Lahen, כבר ביקשו ולא מצאו. Kvar Bikshu V'lo Matzu.
No, if you've already, there's nobody in town who's going to come
over for breakfast.
So
it's a משנה, Mishnah, it's a משנה.
Mishnah. So you investigated this before פסח? Pesach? Before, the day before?
Right, right. You're already, you've already looked. There's nobody in town who's
a כהן Kohen who would come over for breakfast, so you know
this is going to be extra leftover. אמרו לו שמא חוץ לחומה
לנו. Amru Lo Shema Chutz l'Chomah Lanu. Oh, you checked everybody in
town. What if there's those people sleeping outside the city and in
the morning they're going to come in looking for breakfast? אמר
להם,
Amar Lahem,
לדבריכם אף תלויות לא ישרפו שמא יבא אליהו ויטהרם. L'divrechem Af Tluyot
Lo Yisrafu Shema Yavo Eliyahu V'yitaharem. Oh, you want to play what
if, רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says, well then you
can't even burn the ספק safek תרומה Terumah before ערב פסח Erev
Pesach because what if אליהו הנביא Eliyahu HaNavi comes on ערב פסח
Erev Pesach in the morning and.
Can't do what? What if he doesn't come?
I know the גמרא's Gemara going to say, yeah, yeah, very good,
you remember. So what if אליהו הנביא Eliyahu HaNavi comes on שבס
Shabbos morning and he's
going to determine all the ספקות sfekot and he'll say whether it's
טהור tahor or טמא? tamei?
So maybe it'll be טהור tahor and you'll be able to eat
it, so why are you burning it now? He might come tomorrow
and tell you you can eat it.
Yeah, yeah, okay. רש״י Rashi answered my question. The משנה, Mishnah, it's
a משנה Mishnah on מ״ט. mem-tet. It's not that we have a
ברייתא, Baraita, but the משנה Mishnah says.
Okay. והחולין והתרומה חוץ מכדי אכילתו לשבת. v'ha'Chullin v'ha'Terumah chutz michdei achilato
l'Shabbat. Aha. So רש״י Rashi is including that you can put aside
what you're going to eat on on שבס Shabbos חמץ Chametz before
they get to the
תרומה. Terumah. You can put aside even the חמץ Chametz that you're
going to eat on שבת, Shabbat, אבל
כל
מה שעתיד לבער יבער.
aval kol mah she'atid
l'va'er yiva'er. והחולין והתרומה חוץ מכדי אכילתו לשבת. v'ha'Chullin v'ha'Terumah chutz michdei
achilato l'Shabbat.
Yeah,
that's not explicit in the גמרא. Gemara.
Good, thank you.
Where's the רש״י?
Rashi? It's on מ״ט mem-tet in the רש״י. Rashi. The first רש״י
Rashi on the משנה Mishnah on מ״ט. mem-tet. Ah, good. דף מ״ט.
Daf Mem-Tet.
Ah, good. Oh, thank you.
Okay.
So רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says okay, so if you're going to
say what if, say what if אליהו Eliyahu comes. אמרו לו כבר
מובטח להן לישראל שאין אליהו בא לא בערבי שבתות ולא בערבי ימים
טובים מפני הטורח. Amru Lo Kvar Muvtach Lahen l'Yisrael She'ein Eliyahu Ba
Lo b'Arvei Shabbatot v'Lo b'Arvei Yamim Tovim Mipnei ha'Torach. No, we know
אליהו Eliyahu is not going to come on ערב erev on ערב
שבת Erev Shabbat or ערב יום טוב Erev Yom Tov because we're
busy preparing our צ׳ולנט, cholent, so we wouldn't have time. He wouldn't
interfere with our שבת Shabbat preparations. Yeah.
But when we have a, when we have a ברית Brit on
ערב יום טוב, Erev Yom Tov, we always have the אליהו Eliyahu
chair.
Indeed, indeed, but that's a different, different kind of coming of אליהו.
Eliyahu.
It's a phenomenal statement.
Yeah, we had this before, we had this in the, where did
we have it? שבת Shabbos somewhere.
It says that our daily business of building our lives
is
more important than the immediacy of redemption.
Yeah, but we couldn't
point that out last time. Because I'm busy living my life that
הקדוש ברוך הוא HaKadosh Baruch Hu gave me, I have to clean
the cabinets.
Right, or I have to, in this case, I have to prepare
for שבת. Shabbos.
So world redemption is just gonna have to wait till I'm done
with the שמטעס. schmatas.
Would anybody mind אליהו Eliyahu interrupting the פסח Pesach cleaning?
Yeah, no, no, I want to make it clear.
That's a really interesting thought that
even in all of the false messiahs that were in existence in
רש"י's Rashi times, it's probably a reasonable reaction by the rabbis.
Yeah, now to clarify, אליהו Eliyahu could come on ערב פסח, Erev
Pesach, he just won't come on ערב שבת. Erev Shabbos. Right. So
the cleaning, you know, מוחל moichel time. But, but preparing my chicken
for שבת. Shabbos.
But on ערבי ימים
טובים.
arvei
yamim tovim.
ערבי ימים טובים Arvei yamim tovim though, he's not coming.
Right, yeah, no, but now we're talking about the 13th, we're talking
about the 13th, not the 14th.
Oh, you're talking about the 13th, not the 14th.
No, no, no, the 14th, no, שבת Shabbos in the morning, or
it could be the Friday. Yeah.
Alright,
he's done. Yeah, that's right. אמרו. Amru. But
we do open the door for him on the סדר, Seder, I
guess it's, that's not ערב שבת Erev Shabbos anymore. Now he can
come. Now we're ready. Now we have our meal.
We've had our שולחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, now אליהו Eliyahu can
come. Alright, אמרו, Amru, so they said, לא זזו משם עד שקבעו
הלכה כרבי אלעזר בן יהודה איש ברתותא שאומרים משום רבי יהושע, lo
zazu misham ad shekavu halacha k'Rabbi Elazar ben Yehuda ish Bartota she'omrim
mishum Rabbi Yehoshua,
they didn't move from there until they established that indeed the הלכה
halacha is like רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar who says you should not
burn your extra טהור tahor תרומה teruma because what if somebody comes
over and and could eat it? So you can't burn it early.
I'm sorry, I have a question. Is this saying אליהו, Eliyahu, what
is he going to do with what he's going to be מטהר?
metaher?
The ספקות, sfekos, right, the question was about the ספקות. sfekos. So
he's gonna tell you an
הלכה halachic ספק, sfek, not a ספק sfek in fact,
because אליהו Eliyahu isn't going to do what? Well, it's saying he's
going to be מטהר. metaher. So then it's not just a ספק,
safek, I mean, if he's going to be maybe they're really טהור.
tahor. Is he gonna take the תרומה teruma טמא tamei and say
that no, they're טהור? tahor? No, what the גמרא Gemara is saying
is, no, no, there we had three things. The גמרא Gemara said
you can, you should burn the extra
טהור, tahor, טמא, tamei, and תלויים, tulyim, which means there's a ספק
safek about it. So, so what the objection is, if if it's
possible that we'll find out that it's טהור tahor when אליהו Eliyahu
comes, then don't burn it now. Because then somebody will be able
to eat it. There's also a possibility that he'll say it's טמא.
tamei. Right, right, but you can't, but the point is don't burn
it early because it could turn out to be acceptable to eat.
Are they not saying there won't be a concept of טומאה tuma
and טהרה tahara then?
Oh, no, I don't
think so.
I think they're saying that don't burn it now because it might
turn out that you can eat it, and so you can't burn
תרומה teruma until the last minute because
אליהו Eliyahu may come and declare it טהור. tahor. Right, exactly.
But I don't understand that because
it's not prohibited to derive benefit from even טמא tamei תרומה. teruma.
Yes, so
ספק safek טמא tamei תרומה, teruma,
what are you gonna do with it on שבת?
Shabbos? What kind of benefit?
That's true, you can't, you're not going to be able,
well, I guess you could feed it to your animals. Right, and
that's what you would have to do. I was wondering, so if
you don't burn it and it's still left over, then what do
you do?
You, you sell it before,
you sell it to the animals. Oh, right, you could be מבטל
mivatel it, or you could feed it to the animals.
Or you can, you can be מבטל mivatel it. I mean, that's
the easiest answer is, is ביטול. bittul.
It's טמא, tamei, אליהו Eliyahu is טמא. tamei. Okay,
so הלכה halacha is like רבי אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar. מאי לאו אפילו
לאכול? Mai lav afilu l'achol? Does that mean that, that you can
even regarding eating it?
You can eat it until
the fourth, until the fourth hour, until ארבע שעות? arba sha'os? Or
just לא לבער? lo l'va'er? What we're talking about is the fifth
hour when, when you can be
לבער l'va'er it. See רש"י, Rashi, second רש"י Rashi on my
page, לא לבער. lo l'va'er. הדה קבעו כוותיה לא איירי באכילה. Hade
k'vu k'vosei lo airy b'achila. That which we say that the הלכה
halacha is like רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar is not regarding eating, but
אלא בביעור שהיו חבריו חלוקין עליו שלא יבערו טהרות עד למחר. ela
b'vi'ur shehayu chaveirav chalukin alav shelo yiva'aru taharos ad lemachar. The argument
we're talking about is when you burn it, today or tomorrow. So
קבעו ששורפין מערב שבת בשלוש עשרה. k'vu shesorfin me'erev Shabbos b'shlosh esreh.
So they determined that הלכה halacha is like רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar
that you burn it early. אבל בשיעור, Aval b'shi'ur, but as far
as leaving over for the morning, לעולם אימא לך כדי לאכול עד
חמש שעות. l'olam im lacha k'dei l'echol ad chamesh sha'os. How much
do you leave over? To leave this is part of the משנה
mishna that we didn't, I think we didn't get up to in
the.
Oh yeah, I’m sorry I skipped that line when I read it.
כדי לאכול עד ארבע שעות. Kedei leechol ad arba sha’os. So the
question, so what the גמרא Gemara is saying is, are we פוסקנינג
paskening like רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar that you leave over enough to
eat until the fourth hour? Or do you leave over more to
eat until the fifth hour? So the גמרא Gemara answers that when
we say הלכה halacha is like רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, it’s the
idea of when you’re מבער meva’er it, but we’re not saying that
the הלכה halacha is that you have to leave over only enough
until the fourth hour,
implying that really the הלכה halacha is you leave over enough until
the fifth hour. Okay, so how much more can you eat in
the hour? That’s for somebody else to figure out.
And that’s not what we do today.
Well, first of all, we’re talking about תרומה, terumah, so what do
you mean what we do? ואף רבי סבר להא דרב נחמן, V’af
Rebbi savar l’ha d’Rav Nachman,
and רבי Rebbi also agrees with this
what רב נחמן Rav Nachman said, the הלכה halacha like רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, תולין כל חמש. Tolin kol chamesh. דאמר רבין בר רב
אדא, D’amar Ravin bar Rav Adda, רבין Ravin said in the name
of רב אדא, Rav Adda, מעשה באדם אחד שהפקיד דיסקיא מלאה חמץ
אצל יוחנן חקוקא. Ma’aseh b’adam echad shehipkid diskaya mele’ah chametz eitzel Yochanan
Chakuka. A certain person left a bag full of חמץ chametz with
יוחנן חקוקא. Yochanan Chakuka. Yeah,
we had him before. I must have missed that day, I don’t
remember the name. וניקבוה עכברים, Venikvuha achbarim, and mice chewed a hole
through the bag, והיה חמץ מבצבץ ויוצא, Vehaya chametz mevatzbetz veyotzei, and
the חמץ chametz was leaking out. וערב פסח היה, V’erev Pesach haya,
it was ערב פסח, Erev Pesach, ובא לפני רבי, U’va lifnei Rebbi,
and he came to רבי Rebbi to ask what to do, because
on the one hand, you can’t destroy somebody else’s property, on the
other
hand, he sees that it’s חמץ chametz and it’s leaking out and
it’s ערב פסח. Erev Pesach. שעה ראשונה אמר לו המתן, Sha’ah rishonah
amar lo hamten, so the first hour of the day רבי Rebbi
said, wait, wait, maybe he’ll come and take possession of it from
you. שניה אמר לו המתן, Shniyah amar lo hamten, second hour he
said the same thing. שלישית אמר לו המתן, Shlishis amar lo hamten,
you can imagine this guy coming and nudging רבי, Rebbi, well I
know you told me an hour ago to leave it, but now
it’s ten o’clock already, what should I do? אמר לו המתן. Amar
lo hamten. רביעית אמר לו המתן. Revi’is amar lo hamten. חמישית אמר
לו צא ומכור בשוק. Chamishis amar lo tze u’mchor bashuk. And finally,
the fifth hour came, רבי Rebbi said to him, okay, now we’re
done, now you can take it out and sell it in the
marketplace
because that’s the correct
taking care of this guy’s stuff. It’s not edible anymore, so you
might as well try to salvage its value on his behalf by
selling it.
So we can wait until the last possible second before selling our
חמץ. chametz.
Apparently, yeah. I don't know, the shuls are more strict now, they
say you better have it in by six o'clock the day before
or whatever. Why would he say to wait?
Because if the guy that owns it comes back, he won’t have
any use for it, he won’t be able to eat it.
He could eat
it, he could still eat it. Make a nice loaf of bread
and have a nice... yeah, whatever. If it’s
Rice Krispies, you could just pour some milk on it and
eat it. מאי לאו לנכרים, Mai lav l’nochrim, so who are you
going to sell it to? It’s already the fifth hour. Right, so
presumably you sell it to נכרים nochrim like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
that in the fifth
hour, you can get הנאה hana’ah from it, but no Jew can
eat it in the fifth hour, but
you can get הנאה hana’ah from it by selling it to a
נכרי. nochri. אמר רב יוסף לא לישראל. Amar Rav Yosef lo l’Yisrael.
רב יוסף Rav Yosef said not necessarily, לישראל, l’Yisrael, it could be
that he said you could sell it to a Jew, and it’s
like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who says you can keep eating it
until the end.
Yeah. אמר לו אביי אי לישראל נשקול לנפשיה. Amar lo Abaye ei
l’Yisrael nishkul l’nafshei. Ah, so what do you have to sell it
for?
You eat it in the fifth hour, right? Or you buy it
from yourself on behalf of the
owner. Take twenty dollars out of your pocket and put it in
an envelope and you eat it. What do you have to take
it to the marketplace for? If that’s what we’re talking
about. משום חשדא. Mishum chashada. That you can’t do because that doesn’t
look right. People will suspect that you’re giving yourself a better price.
Maybe this is fifty dollars worth of stuff and you’re paying
twenty. דתניא, D’tanya, we have a ברייתא braisa in a similar case.
גבאי צדקה שאין להם עניים לחלק. Gabbai tzedakah she’ein lahem aniyim l’chalek.
If you have money in the פושקא pushka and you have nobody
to give it to. פורטין לאחרים ואין פורטין לעצמן. Portin l’acherim v’ein
portin l’atzman. So you know you have all the quarters and nickels
and dimes and pennies in the פושקא pushka and it’s full, you
need to empty it out. So what do you do? You take
it to the bank and you roll them up and you get
bills, right? So same thing here.
You exchange the money to somebody else. You have to take it
to the bank.
You can’t roll up the quarters and keep them for yourself for
the laundry and put in a dollar bill instead
yourself. Similarly, גבאי תמחוי שאין להם עניים לחלק, Gabbai tamchui she’ein lahem
aniyim l’chalek, and if you’re managing a soup kitchen and you have
leftover soup and you don’t have anyone to give it
to. מוכרין לאחרים ואין מוכרין לעצמן. Mochrin l’acherim v’ein mochrin l’atzman. You
sell it to somebody else. You can’t take the soup home and
pay the twenty dollars for it to the
soup kitchen account. You have to sell it to somebody else and
take the money from
them. Same
reason. משום חשדא. Mishum chashada. שנאמר והייתם נקיים מה' ומישראל shene'emar v'heyitem
nekiyim me'Hashem u'miYisrael
because it says
והייתם נקיים מה' ומישראל, v'heyitem nekiyim me'Hashem u'miYisrael, you should be clean
from from God and from Israel. So in other words you have
to look good not only to God but also to people. You
can't you have to be careful about what people will think.
It's interesting, it's not really מראית עין marit ayin though, it seems
to me. It seems like it's stronger than that. It seems like
you're yes, it's like you could theoretically you could easily embezzle in
these types of situations.
מראית עין marit ayin is different. מראית עין marit ayin is people
will think that they're allowed to do what you're doing. Here it's
the question that they're suspecting you of doing something wrong.
And and it's tempting. It's like naturally tempting. I don't know, I
haven't thought it through yet completely but it's a
different concept than מראית עין.
marit ayin. It really, yeah, it sounds like it's similar, but מראית
עין marit
ayin is people are going to be they'll think something else, they're
going to be lenient about it, they're going to think oh this
is okay, and and this is people will be suspicious about it
thinking who does this guy think he is, we know what we
know what he's really after. Yes, it's suspected as now is now
as though, as though one of the things to suspect him of
is something that's stuck upon him, something. Never has there been
corruption in the
Jewish people.
In מסכת פאה Masechet Pe'ah they actually require that
charity administrators work in pairs or threes. And רמב"ם Rambam brings down
that as הלכה. halacha. You can't have a single charity administrator. Right.
And how can you be effective as
this?
But we know nowadays every everything. רמב"ם Rambam said all communities have
such a such a system. Okay, let's go on. אמר ליה רב
אדא בר מתנא לרב יוסף, amar leh Rav Adda bar Mattana l'Rav
Yosef, בפירוש אמרת לן, beferush amrat lan, you told us specifically, צא
ומכרן לנכרים כרבי יהודה. tze u'mochran l'nochrim k'Rabbi Yehuda. We don't have
to wonder about who does he mean you can sell it to.
You told us when you related this this
story you said צא ומכרן לנכרים כרבי יהודה tze u'mochran l'nochrim k'Rabbi
Yehuda when you go and sell it in the fifth hour it's
to non-Jews. So and to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. These are consistent
with what
רב יוסף Rav Yosef said above, איסורא כרבי מאיר. issura k'Rabbi Meir.
Now they're saying oh no what do you mean, why are you
saying איסורא כרבי מאיר? issura k'Rabbi Meir? He said the...
Yeah,
right.
Right. Yeah, another case where רב יוסף Rav Yosef had forgotten what
he what he taught so they're reminding him. אמר רב יוסף כמאן
אזלא הא שמעתא דרב כרבן שמעון בן גמליאל.
amar Rav Yosef k'man
azla ha shemata d'Rav k'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. Who does this go
according
to? Like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. דתנן, d'tnan,
it's the משנה, mishna, המפקיד פירות אצל חבירו אפילו הן אבודין לא
יגע בהן. hamapkid peirot etzel chaveiro afilu hen avudin lo yiga bahen.
In general, nothing to do with חמץ, chametz, a person gives fruit
to to his friend to watch for him. Even if they are
rotting, even if they're going to be to be destroyed, to be
lost, לא יגע בהן, lo yiga bahen, you should not touch them.
You know he gave you a bag of a bag of apples,
just leave them where they are. It doesn't matter if
if
they are going back. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר מוכרין בבית דין
מפני השבת אבידה. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer mochrin b'veit din mipnei
hashavat aveidah. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says no,
this is not tenable. Let's treat this as as a lost item
and go to בית דין beit din and sell it through their
agent. So at least when the guy comes back he won't have
worthless rotten apples, he'll have the money from whatever you were able
to sell the apples for while they were still
good. אמר ליה אביי, amar leh Abaye, ולאו איתמר עלה, v'lav itmar
alah, didn't we have a didn't we learn about that? אמר רבה
בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar
Rabbi Yochanan, לא שנו אלא בכדי חסרונה. lo shanu ela bichdei chesronah.
That's only
if
you you have to leave them as they are only if they
are rotting at a at the usual rate. In other words there's
always going to be some spoilage and people accept that. If I
have, you know, a bushel of apples, I know that some of
them are not going to be are going to be going bad
after a few
weeks. אבל יותר מכדי חסרונה, aval yoter michdei chesronah, but if for
some reason they are rotting at a faster rate than then would
be expected, then מוכרין בבית דין, mochrin b'veit din, then you sell
them through בית דין. beit din. וכל שכן הכא דאבידה לגמרי, v'chol
sheken hacha d'aveida legamrei, and certainly in the case of חמץ chametz
where, you know, once the sixth hour hits or the fifth hour,
then you've lost them completely. So that's certainly a case that's even
worse than יותר מכדי חסרונה. yoter michdei chesronah. You know that you're
going to lose everything, so certainly in the case of חמץ chametz
you have to you should take them and sell them whether through
בית דין beit din or or as in the שוק shuk in
this case. ודתני רבי יהודה. v'detani Rabbi Yehuda. See decide?
Yeah, we finished with the fifth hour now, כולה לחסא? kulah l'chasa?
What about the fifth hour? Yeah, yeah, רבי
יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda.
Yeah. ודתני רבי יהודה שתי חלות. v'detani Rabbi Yehuda shtei chalot. So
let's look back on the משנה. mishna. The case was... This was
for רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, these are חלות התודה.
chalot hatoda. Yeah. The case in the משנה Mishnah was: eat two,
you lay out two, one's taken away, you don't do anything, and
then both of them
you
burn.
Yeah,
well this was the sign: שתי חלות של תודה פסולות מונחות Shtei
chalos shel Todah psulos munachos על גבי האיצטבא. al gabei ha'itztaba. There
were two, this was the sign of how they signaled when you
should destroy the חמץ. chametz. There were two loaves of תודה Todah
which were פסולות, psulos, which were on the bench in the בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. כל זמן שמונחות, Kol zman shemunachos, when they were
both sitting there, כל העם אוכלין, kol ha'am ochlin, so you knew
you could still eat. ניטלה אחת, Nitla achas, they took one away,
that was the sign תולין, tolin, that was no more eating, but
you can still הנאה hana'ah from it, ולא אוכלין ולא שורפין. v'lo
ochlin v'lo sorfin. ניטלו שתיהן, Nitlu shteihen, if once both of them
were removed, התחילו כל העם שורפין, hischilu kol ha'am sorfin, then you
know it's burning time. Where was that?
You had
to be right
near.
Yeah, I know, it's a little strange. Where's that
משנה?
Mishnah? That's the משנה Mishnah we're dealing with now, it's on י"א
עמוד ב'. Yud Aleph amud Beis. י"א עמוד ב'. Yud Aleph amud
Beis.
Yeah, it's in the middle of the משנה. Mishnah.
Oh, just imagine.
Right, so this whole thing about how they
knew whether there's one loaf of חלה challah or two, or any
loaf.
So there generally seems to be an assumption, the way I understand
it, that word spreads quickly. And you see that in various cases.
You know, you see that with regarding... just like a local rumor
mill. Yeah, I guess so.
By the time it
spreads, the hour's gone.
I know,
we're talking about one hour here.
I know, so maybe it's
the idea of the ideal situation.
It seems to
be only the כהנים Kohanim would see this.
Well
no,
not that, I don't think so, because remember we're talking about ערב
פסח Erev Pesach and everybody's there for the רגל, regel, right?
So it's probably crowded and word spreads quickly, you know. But so
it doesn't...
it
only spreads to the people there,
I
mean who are hanging around. Yeah, people, I think we can assume
that this only applies to people who were in a position to
either see it directly or to hear the news. But you know,
now you imagine they
could have blown the שופר, shofar, that would have been more effective,
you know, two blasts. The משנה's Mishnah's language is גב האיצטבא. gav
ha'itztaba. Yeah, some sort of platform was
there.
Yeah, Artscroll translated it as a bench. We'll see, the גמרא Gemara
will
discuss what the איצטבא itztaba is. Maybe like a round room with
flags that you could see from far. But it doesn't say they
were flags. Right, no, it doesn't, but that may be the part
that some media say that this is a symbol, like a timer,
like a clock you'd put forward.
Since we're discussing about a clock, so this may be just one
loaf of bread big enough, maybe, not just a small loaf that
we use today. The point is, the point is that there was
a signal in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. How far that signal
spread is not discussed here. And now the גמרא Gemara is going
to discuss what the nature of תודה פסולה Todah psulah and first
it's going to discuss what is the איצטבא. itztaba.
But what does רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir do with it?
I mean, clearly this seems to support רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's view.
Oh yeah, because well, עוד אמר רבי יהודה. od amar Rabbi Yehuda.
Right, I'm saying so what does רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir say?
Was no חלה? challah? I mean, like what would he do with
that?
Yeah,
that's a good question. I mean, did this actually happen? So why
it would be אסור assur for...
because what do you do up until the fifth...
until the fifth hour?
Let's, let's keep going, we have a lot to cover.
Just to address that point, I
mean, how did disagreements arise in any case? Like some of these
are reporting what his tradition is, right, what he heard from his
teacher. So nobody's denying that that's what he heard from his teacher.
In the case of a מעשה שהיה, ma'aseh shehayah, these things also
can be garbled in transmission, right? Because if you have the dissonance
of... sorry... if you have the dissonance of what you think the
הלכה halacha is and what this story is, I mean the גמרא
Gemara does it all the time, right? Is you kind of twist
the story or twist your opinion so that they match. So, you
know, this was רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's story, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
maybe would have said that's not the way it happened or, you
know. Okay, let's go.
To fringe the issue, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda had the same teacher and got it from the same person
and still they have their
opinions. Okay, תני תנא קמיה דרבי יהודה. Tani tanna kamei d'Rabbi Yehuda.
A תנא tanna learned before רבי יהודה: Rabbi Yehuda: על גב האיצטבא,
al gav ha'itztaba, on the bench, that's where the חלה challah was.
אמר ליה וכי לצניוען הוא צריך Amar lei: V'chi litzni'un hu tzarich?
So, do you put it on the bench? Who can see it?
Right? You're not putting it there in a low place to keep
it quiet, you're doing it as a signal. תני על גג האיצטבא.
Tani: Al gag ha'itztaba. What it should say is on the roof
of the איצטבא. itztaba. So these are benches with covers on them,
that's higher up in the עזרה, azarah, I think. The גמרא Gemara
will describe what it's
like. על גג האיצטבא, Al gag ha'itztaba, on the roof. So there
was a cover over the
benches, so that's, that's where it was a high place. אמר רב
אשי אמר רבי יהודה: Amar Rav Ashi amar Rabbi Yehuda: הר הבית
אסטיו כפול היה. Har Habayis istav kaphul hayah. The הר הבית Har
Habayis had a double row of benches around it. תניא נמי הכי.
Tanya nami hachi. And that's what we're talking about. Well, I'm going
with the Artscroll translation, but yeah, you're right, the Steinsaltz has columns.
Yes, it's a basilica.
I don't even know what a basilica is. Columns. Thank you. תניא
נמי הכי.
Tanya nami
hachi. Okay, תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, הר הבית סטיו כפול
היה.
Har Habayis stav
kaful haya. The הר הבית Har Habayis had double row of columns.
רבי יהודה אומר איסטוונית הייתה נקראת. Rabbi Yehuda omer istavanis haysa nikres.
It was called an איסטוונית, istavanis, which was like the apparently
the the market streets were set up like this also and you
see that in Roman ruins all the time, right? There are columns
along the main street and so the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash was
set up in a similar
way. סטיו לפני סטיו. stav lifnim mistav. One one row of columns
in between behind the other one.
Okay so where was this איסטוונית?
istavanis? הר הבית. Har Habayis. That's as specific as as we get.
So it's not in the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash?
Oh yeah, you're right. I'm sorry, not in the עזרה. Azara. I
misstated. You're correct.
So there's some sort of platform on הר הבית. Har Habayis. Is
this some- does it have to do with these columns or is
this separate? Or separate?
Well what do columns have to do with the platform? Because there
was a platform above the above the columns. So they put some
platform on a
column, someone went up on a column? Yeah, sure. You see that
all the time. There was a roof.
Yeah, that's the columns were supporting something.
A roof. A roof? A roof of these columns. Yeah, so the
people could see it. He expanded הר הבית, Har Habayis, he made
this gigantic Roman edifice that was a basilica with a stoa and
a roof. Where? Where?
On the stoa of הר הבית.
Har Habayis. Oh columns. Okay.
Up up above the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and high above it.
No, not part of it, but near it.
And they put it there. Which so that's- so Rivka, so a
lot more people could see it if it was up on top
of a high place.
A platform for going up.
Yeah. Okay. פסולות. Psulos. Now we're going to talk about the תודה
Toda or the חלות chalos of the תודה. Toda. What makes them
פסולות? psulos? אמאי פסולות? Amai psulos? Why do they- why were they
פסולות? psulos? אמר רבי חנינא Amar Rabbi Chanina מתוך שהיו מרובות mitoch
she-hayu merubos נפסלות בלינה. nifsalos belina. Because there were a lot of
them, they became פסולות psulos because a תודה Toda can only be
eaten a day and the night and sorry, a day and a
night. In the morning they become they become
leftover and they're פסולות. psulos. דתניא, Detanya, we have a ברייתא, braisa,
אין מביאין תודה בחג המצות. ein mevi'im Toda be-Chag HaMatzos. You can't
bring a קרבן תודה Korban Toda on פסח Pesach מפני חמץ שבה
mipnei chametz she-ba because of because it involves loaves which are חמץ.
chametz. פשיטא. Pshita. Yeah, duh. אמר רב אדא בר אהבה Amar Rav
Adda bar Ahava הכא בארבעה עשר עסקינן. hacha bearba'ah asar askinan. We're
not talking about on חג המצות, Chag HaMatzos, on פסח, Pesach, we're
talking about the
fourteenth. וקסבר Vekasavar אין מביאים קדשים לבית הפסול. ein mevi'im kodshim le-veis
hapsul. You you
can't bring on the fourteenth because even though it's still edible, but
it will become inedible
before the time when they finish.
Right. So last ערב פסח Erev Pesach in the שול, shul, the
שליח ציבור shliach tzibbur goofed and said מזמור לתודה. Mizmor le-Toda. Uh-huh.
So according to this, he actually was okay.
He was okay.
Okay. וכולי עלמא וכולי עלמא בשלושה עשר מייתו להו. Vechuli alma vechuli
alma bishlosha asar mayisu lehu. Everybody would bring their תודה Toda on
the thirteenth. ומתוך שהן מרובות, Umitoch she-hein merubos, because they're a lot
of- because they're a lot, נפסלו בלינה. nifselu belina. They would become
פסולות psulos בלינה. belina. What does it mean? Because you know we
have this view like alright, just go bring your תודה, Toda, but
not everyone was always up for
the- yeah, it was busy. I mean on the fourteenth- people came,
שלוש רגלים,
shalosh regalim, and they brought
whatever it is they needed to. So I guess whoever needed to
bring the תודה Toda just waited until doing עליה לרגל. aliyah laregel.
So either they would have brought it שבועות Shavuos or they could
have brought it סוכות Succos or פסח Pesach was one of the
other three times they'd bring it. And since everyone's coming then, that's
when they bring it. Right. So they brought it on the thirteenth
but the thing is because because there's so many
people,
there's too much bread. Who can eat all that bread? So that's
why that's why you would have פסולות, psulos, you'd have לינה, lina,
you'd have פסולות. psulos. And you need to bring a
lot of
bread with it.
Yeah, forty loaves, right? Right. And then- sorry?
לינה Lina meaning it was left over. Which means sorry? לינה. Lina.
Yeah, leftover. What is leftover? Yeah, yeah. Yeah, that's why there were
leftovers because there was so much bread on the day
before. Right. Okay. רבי ינאי אומר Rabbi Yannai omer כשרות היו. kesheros
hayu. Rabbi Yannai says no, these weren't פסולות psulos loaves of the
תודה, Toda, they were regular, they were כשר. kasher. ואמאי קרו להו
פסולות? Ve-amai karu lehu psulos? Why do we call them פסולות? psulos?
שלא נשחט עליהן הזבח. She-lo nishchat aleihen hazavach. Because we're talking about
loaves which the which the- so what happens is you bring the
קרבן, korban, once you've slaughtered the קרבן korban and sprinkled the blood,
then you get to eat the bread. Okay. But until you've done
so, you can't eat the bread yet. So what we're saying is
we haven't gotten around to- so these are not פסולות psulos loaves,
but they're loaves which the תודה Toda hasn't been slaughtered yet.
Why would they put it up on a platform?
Everyone needs to eat it. So I guess you could eat it
when you bring it down. Like that- maybe this is the signal,
it's like, okay, last chance to eat your חמץ, chametz, I'm getting
my תודה Toda to eat now.
Oh, you thought that the loaves of the תודה Toda on this
platform were like all the loaves of the תודה? Toda? No,
no.
It says there were two. They were two, but it's a signal.
It's a signal. We're gonna take, we're gonna take
תודה todah loaves, two תודה todah loaves and put them up there
as the signal. And the גמרא Gemara said what we take loaves
which are פסול. pasul. But the ברייתא baraita said we take loaves
the משנה Mishnah said we're taking loaves that are פסול. pasul. So
now the גמרא Gemara is saying what kind of פסול pasul and
why do they have to be פסול? pasul? And now it's saying
that they're not actually פסול, pasul, they're just not edible yet because
they're not they're in a state of limbo because you didn't do
the
שחיטה shechitah of the זבח zevach yet. So, נשחט, nishchat, so the
גמרא Gemara says, so yeah, so like why are you
not slaughtering it? שאבד הזבח, she-avad hazevach, oh it got lost, you
don't know it wandered off and you can't do the
שחיטה. shechitah. ונייתי זבח אחר ונשחט, v'naiiti zevach acher v'nishchat, so the
גמרא Gemara says that's alright, just bring another one. The loaves haven't
yet been if the loaves are not designated as part of this
particular תודה todah yet, then bring another תודה todah and do the
שחיטה shechitah on them and then the loaves
are good. דאמר זאת תודה ואלו לחמה, d'amar zot todah v'elo lachma,
if you designate these loaves are for this
תודה, todah, then they're linked and if you end up for whatever
reason not being able to slaughter that תודה, todah, then you're at
a loss.
Alright, so now we're saying
they're not פסול pasul then? We're treated as פסול? pasul? Yeah, yeah,
because כשרות היו.
kesherot hayu.
Right, but they're called פסולות psulot not because they're פסול, pasul, they're
not yet edible.
I'm saying, no, but now we're saying this,
maybe we were treating them as
פסול. pasul. Ah, yeah, you'll never be able to
right, right, you'll never be able to eat them. וכי דרבא, v'chi
d'Rava, דאמר רבא, d'amar Rava, אבד הלחם מביא לחם אחר, avad halechem
mevi lechem acher, רבא Rava said if you lost the לחם, lechem,
you lost the bread, then you can bake other bread. אבדת תודה
אין מביא תודה אחר, avdat todah ein mevi todah acher, but if
you lost the תודה todah you cannot bring another תודה. todah. מאי
טעמא, mai ta'ama, לחם גלל תודה, lechem glal todah, why is that?
Because the bread was brought as
an accessory to the קרבן, korban, to the תודה, todah, ואין תודה
גלל לחם, v'ein todah glal lechem, but it's not the other way
around. So
the גמרא Gemara says ונפרקינהו ונפקינהו לחולין. v'nifrikinhu v'nafkinhu l'chullin. Okay, so
you have this bread, why are you calling it פסול? pasul? You
could you could redeem it, right, you could exchange it for other
bread and make this or
with money you could make it חולין. chullin.
No, it's like redeeming it. Look at רש"י. Rashi.
What is this ונפרקינהו v'nifrikinhu though? Oh, redeem and then make it
חולין. chullin. Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, so אלא, ela, so the גמרא Gemara retreats from that whole
thing and says לעולם שנשחט הזבח. l'olam shenishchat ha-zevach. Alright, we're talking
about where we did do the שחיטה shechitah of the קרבן, korban,
but ונשפך הדם, v'nishpach hadam, we couldn't do the זריקת הדם, zrikat
hadam, couldn't sprinkle the blood because it spilled.
וכמאן כרבי, v'chuman k'Rabbi, and this is according to רבי, Rabbi, דאמר
רבי שני דברים המתירין מעלין זה בלא זה. d'amar Rabbi shnei devarim
hamattirin maalin zeh b'lo zeh. You have two
actions which are required for the לחם lechem to be eaten, which
are the שחיטה, shechitah, the slaughtering, and the זריקה, zrika, the sprinkling
of
the blood. מעלין
זה
בלא זה,
maalin zeh
b'lo zeh, which means... yeah, if you've done only one of those
actions, only the שחיטה, shechitah, then the bread becomes קדוש kadosh even
though it's not edible yet because it needs the second thing, the
sprinkling. דתניא, d'tanya, as we have a ברייתא, baraita, כבשי עצרת אין
מקדשין את הלחם אלא בשחיטה. kivsei atzeret ein mekaddeshin es halechem ela
b'shechitah. When it comes to the שתי הלחם shtei halechem on שבועות,
Shavuot, it's the same idea. You have two lambs and you have
loaves of bread. So the שחיטה shechitah is what makes the bread
holy. כיצד, keitzad, how does this work? שחטן לשמן וזרק דמן לשמן
קידש הלחם. shchaton lishman v'zarak daman lishman kidash halechem. If you did
everything right, you did the שחיטה, shechitah, you did the זריקה, zrika,
the bread is
holy. שחטן שלא לשמן וזרק דמן שלא לשמן לא קידש הלחם. shchaton
shelo lishman v'zarak daman shelo lishman lo kidash halechem. If you did
everything wrong, you did the שחיטה shechitah for the sake of some
other קרבן, korban, you did the זריקה zrika for the sake of
some other קרבן, korban, and so there's no שתי הלחם shtei halechem
קרבן korban brought
here, the bread is not has no status at all. שחטן לשמן,
shchaton lishman, but what if you did the שחיטה shechitah of the
sheep
properly for the correct purpose, וזרק דמן שלא לשמן, v'zarak daman shelo
lishman, and you did the זריקה zrika for the incorrect
purpose? So לחם קדוש ואינו קדוש. lechem kadosh v'eino kadosh. Now it's
in limbo. It's sanctified but you can't eat it because it hasn't
been
completed, the blood wasn't correctly
sprinkled. דברי רבי. divrei Rabbi. רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Elazar
bar Rabbi Shimon omer, לעולם אינו קדוש הלחם עד שישחוט לשמן ויזרוק
דמן לשמן. l'olam eino kadosh halechem ad sheyishchat lishman v'yizrok daman lishman.
רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says no, it's in or out. You know,
if it's if you didn't do both of the required actions, then
it doesn't acquire any special status at all, the bread.
So so and now the גמרא Gemara says no, אפילו תימא רבי
אלעזר ברבי שמעון. afilu teima Rabbi Elazar bar Rabbi Shimon. You could
even interpret what we're saying according to רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi
Elazar bar Rabbi Shimon because what are they talking about there?
הכא במאי עסקינן כגון שנתקבל הדם בכוס ונשפך. hacha bemai askinan kegon
shenitkabel hadam bakos v'nishpach. We're talking about what are we talking about?
When so you did the שחיטה, shechitah, you got the blood in
the bowl, you're ready to do the זריקה, zrika, so now it's
קדוש. kadosh. Why? Even though you didn't do
the זריקה zerika yet. רבי אלעזר בר שמעון Rabbi Elazar bar Shimon
סבר כאבוה, savar ke'avuh, רבי אלעזר בר שמעון Rabbi Elazar bar Shimon
holds like his father דאמר כל העומד לזרוק כזרק דמי. de'amar kol
ha'omed lizrok kezarak dami. Once it's ready to be sprinkled, you've got
it in the bowl, then כזרק דמי, kezarak dami, then
the bread becomes the bread is now קדוש kadosh and can be
eaten. Now later it spills and doesn't end up being
you don't end up doing the זריקה zerika and it's no longer
possible to do the זריקה zerika then we reexamine it and say
it's not we retreat from that position and it's not קדוש kadosh
anymore. Right. The bread.
Yes. So what were we saying?
Next what kind of חלות chalot do we have here? Yeah so
we kind of lost that thread right? I mean the whole thing
was kind of a semantic exercise because
since the משנה Mishna said they use חלות פסולות chalot pesulot so
we're investigating how can חלות chalot become פסולות. pesulot. So whatever they
because there
were so many people there it was יסבעו לה. yisav'u lah.
Right. But and then but then we kind of got off onto
a tangent of how does how does this bread become
פסול? pasul? Is it פסול pasul if you only do one of
the עבודה avodah only the שחיטה shechita not the זריקה? zerika? So
you have all these different opinions. So what exactly they did use
in the במקדש be'Mikdash is not really the point here I think.
I mean the משנה Mishna just mentioned in an offhanded way they
use חלות פסולות chalot pesulot and that that gave the גמרא Gemara
an opportunity to examine how exactly can חלות chalot become פסולות pesulot
under what circumstances
after שחיטה shechita after זריקה zerika right this kind of hybrid opinion
is there a תלוי taluy is there a you know a little
bit pregnant status? It's kind of it's kind of irrelevant.
And probably maybe this was because רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir doesn't have
a tradition at all or you know or we have to learn
it differently because otherwise it would be a problem to his viewpoint.
Even according to רבי יהודה Rebbi
Yehuda I'm not even sure exactly the circumstances of you know what
they did. Yeah so look it's a tangent. I mean we're really
going off on a tangent and I don't think that רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda was really you know
concerned with exactly all this but the גמרא Gemara uses the opportunity
to investigate the parameters of what is how does the לחם lechem
become
פסול pasul and under what circumstances. תנו משום רבי אלעזר אמרו tanu
mishum Rabbi Elazar amru כשרות
היו. kesherot hayu. So we said before רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says
no they were חלות כשרות. chalot kesherot. כל זמן שמונחות כל העם
אוכלין. kol zman shemunachot kol ha'am ochlin. As long as they were
there you could eat the חמץ. chametz. ניטלה אחת מהן תולין. nitlah
achas meihen tolin. Once they took away one חלה challa you knew
it was time to stop eating. לא אוכלין ולא שורפין lo ochlin
velo sorfin don't eat but you don't have to burn it
yet. ניטלו שתיהן התחילו כולם שורפין nitlu shteihen hischilu kulam sorfin then
they all started burning. תניא
אבא שאול אומר tanya Abba Shaul omer שתי פרות היו חורשות בהר
המשחה shtei parot hayu chorshos b'Har haMishcha there was a different signal
having to do with bread the signal was there were two cows
that were plowing in הר המשחה Har haMishcha which was on הר
הזיתים Har haZeisim I guess. Yeah Steinshaltz says הר הזיתים. Har haZeisim.
Yeah כל זמן
ששתיהן חורשות כל העם אוכלין
kol zman she'shteihen
chorshos
kol ha'am ochlin as long as they were both plowing and by
the way this is also like this you could see from far
away right if you're on הר הבית Har haBayis or in ירושלים
Yerushalayim and you have a wider view of הר הזיתים. Har haZeisim.
I know it's not everybody but
whatever. כל זמן ששתיהן חורשות כל העם אוכלין. kol zman she'shteihen chorshos
kol ha'am ochlin. ניטלה אחת מהן תולין nitlah achas meihen tolin once
they removed one of the cows תולין. tolin. לא אוכלין ולא שורפין
lo ochlin velo sorfin you couldn't do anything. ניטלו שתיהן התחילו כל
העם שורפין nitlu shteihen hischilu kol ha'am sorfin once both cows were
removed from the field. Yeah this is even more problematic.
Go go look outside. How many cows? How many oxen are there?
I don't know I can't see from here. Are those the ones?
Wait whose cows are those? All right by the way I just
want to say I just want to say that I
will try to distribute by email a nice introduction in the ArtScroll
to the next משנה Mishna which is so it's going to go
on for a week and the and it's all about טומאה וטהרה
tumah v'taharah and the different levels of טומאה tumah and so on
so I will try if I can make a copy to send
it out by email. Is that fair use? You think you're the
copyright expert. Is that fair use?
Probably. By the way I hate to say this but cows don't
plow oxen plow it should be פרים. parim.